Edward Franklin Williams papers, 1859-1918.
Congregational Library & Archives
Edward Franklin Williams papers, 1859-1918.
MS4981
Congregational Library & Archives
1.88 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
Edward Franklin Williams was born in Uxbridge, Massachusetts on July 22, 1832. He graduated from Yale in 1856 after which he spent three years teaching in Connecticut and Massachusetts. He then went to the Princeton Theological Seminary where he graduated in 1861. He was licensed by the Presbytery of New Brunswick in 1861. When the Civil War broke out, Williams joined the Christian Commission where he distributed religious literature, medical aid, and various supplies to Union troops. The Congregational ministry at Whitinsville, Massachusetts ordained Williams on October 17, 1866. After 1891, Williams was a delegate to the International Congregational Council in London, England. He spent several years abroad and studied at the University of Berlin after which he published "Christian Life in Germany" in 1896. From 1901-1911, Williams was the pastor of the First Congregational Church of Evanston in Evanston, Illinois where he died on May 26, 1919. This collection consists of the personal papers of Edward Franklin Williams that were presumably collected by Williams himself. The collection includes sermons, notes, writings, and lectures given at various institutions. Of particular note are his sermons, which are labeled with the various dates, and locations he gave them as well as marked with edits and changes he made to them over the years. His writings include notes and research on a variety of topics ranging from the early years of American history to the study of electricity. Also included are the lectures he gave at the Chicago Theological Seminary and Beloit College on systemic theology and the history of philosophy.
Williams, Edward F. (Edward Franklin), 1832-1919
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Collection arrived at the CLA as part of a large deposit of materials from the Chicago Theological Seminary in January 2011; Acc# 2011-19. An additional accrual arrived in 2015.
Biographical Information
Edward Franklin Williams was born in Uxbridge, Massachusetts on July 22, 1832. He graduated from Yale in 1856 after which he spent three years teaching in Connecticut and Massachusetts. He then went to the Princeton Theological Seminary where he graduated in 1861. He was licensed by the Presbytery of New Brunswick in 1861. When the Civil War broke out, Williams joined the Christian Commission where he distributed religious literature, medical aid, and various supplies to Union troops. The Congregational ministry at Whitinsville, Massachusetts ordained Williams on October 17, 1866. He took charge of the Lookout Mountain Institute in Chattanooga, Tennessee in 1866 where he educated young missionaries. After a brief time as a teacher in the Normal Department of Howard University in Washington, D.C., he moved west and began preaching in St. Charles, Illinois in 1869. From 1869-1873, Williams was the pastor of Tabernacle Congregational Church in Chicago Illinois. He then moved on to a pastorate at the South Congregational Church in Chicago, Illinois from 1873-1891. After 1891, Williams was a delegate to the International Congregational Council in London, England. He spent several years abroad and studied at the University of Berlin after which he published "Christian Life in Germany" in 1896. Williams served as the Editor of the Congregationalist, Director of the Chicago Missionary Society, and president of the Chicago Tract Society which published and distributed Christian literature. Additionally, Williams lectured at the Chicago Theological Seminary in 1894 and Beloit College in 1903. From 1901-1911, Williams was the pastor of the First Congregational Church of Evanston in Evanston, Illinois where he died on May 26, 1919.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the personal papers of Edward Franklin Williams that were presumably collected by Williams himself. The collection includes sermons, notes, writings, and lectures given at various institutions. Of particular note are his sermons, which are labeled with the various dates, and locations he gave them as well as marked with edits and changes he made to them over the years. His writings include notes and research on a variety of topics ranging from the early years of American history to the study of electricity. Also included are the lectures he gave at the Chicago Theological Seminary and Beloit College on systemic theology and the history of philosophy.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the three series listed below. Materials each series is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Writings and Notes, 1859-1915.
Series 2: Sermons, 1862-1918.
Series 3: Lectures, 1870-1918.
Related Materials
Additional records related to the works of Edward Franklin Williams can be found in the Chicago, Ill. Tabernacle Congregational Church records, 1865-1906, 1911, RG5216.
Clergy -- United States.; Diaries.; Lectures and lecturing.; Religion and science.; Sermons, American.; Beloit College -- Lectures and lecturing.; Princeton Theological Seminary.; South Congregational Church (Chicago, Ill.); Tabernacle Congregational Church (Chicago, Ill.); United States Christian Commission. Army Committee
- Writings and notes, 1859 1915; 1859-1915; 24 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains a variety of writings by Edward Franklin Williams and a few others. The materials are arranged chronologically. Also included is an extensive set of notes on a range of topics from the history of Holland to science.
  - Diary, 1859 1860; 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 124)
    This series contains diary materials written by Edward Franklin Williams. The majority of the diary seems to have been written while Williams was attending Princeton Theological Seminary and living in the area. The materials are arranged according to original order as a number of the loose pages are undated.
  - Diary, 1860 1865; 1860-1865 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Yale and James T. Graves, 1864 1866; 1864-1866 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    This file contains a scrapbook of Yale memorabilia. Though Williams attended Yale, the dates of the materials are ten years after Williams graduated. There are also a number of materials addressed to James T. Graves, who was also a minister in the Chicago area. This collection kept this file because it most likely was held on to by Williams on purpose.
  - Congregational House, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Notes, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Notes on Herbert Spencer, April 1903 (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Protestant Weekly Letter by Professor Doctor Adolf Deissmann, August 21, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Religion and Science, undated (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Jesuits and Settlements in America, undated (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Peace of Utrecht notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - La Salle notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Notes on Atheism, undated (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Supplementary Notes from Palfrey and Bancroft Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Notes on Judgement, undated (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - New Platonism, undated (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Notes on Holland, undated (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Notes on George Eliot, undated (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Hebrew Syntax notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Untitled notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Notes on the Social Question or Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Notes on Rationale of Philosophical Thought, undated (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Set of Religious Questions, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes on Poetry, Philosophy and Ethics, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Sermons, 1862 1918; 1862-1918; 128 Folders
  This series contains sermons written and used by Edward Franklin Williams across his career. Most sermons indicate all the places and dates they were preached. The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Sermons first Preached at Rockdale Congregational Church, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - In the Vineyard, July 23, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sermons first Preached at St. Charles Church, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sermons first Preached at Tabernacle Congregational Church, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Untitled sermon, February 14, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Untitled sermon, March 28, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Untitled sermon, April 11, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Untitled sermon, June 6, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Mustard Seed, May 22, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermons first Preached at Tabernacle Congregational Church, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sermons first Preached at Tabernacle Congregational Church, 1870 1871; 1870-1871 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Common place book, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Untitled sermons, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Joseph, on a Life of Trust, April 16, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Untitled sermons, April 23, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Insanity of Sin, May 7, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Pharisee and the Publieum, July 16, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Untitled sermons, August 23, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sermons first Preached at Tabernacle Congregational Church, 1871 1873; 1871-1873 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kingdom of God: Permanent and Universal, March 17, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Spirits, June 9, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Significant of the Resurrection of Jesus, June 9, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Untitled sermon, March 23, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sermons first Preached at Tabernacle Congregational Church, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sermons delivered at Oakland Congregational Church, October 1875 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Untitled sermon, December 5, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Thankfulness, an Element in the Christian Life, November 10, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Greed, February 9, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Church Warfare, February 16, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Untitled sermons, 1879 1883; 1879-1883 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Thanksgiving, November 25, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Manifestation of God, April 6, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - A New Outlook, January 6, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Atonement as Set Forth in the Gospels, March 10, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Thinking, June 19, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Power of Example, August 21, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Perfection in Manhood, August 25, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mormonism, November 21, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Debt the West Owes the East, November 24, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - House of the Lord, March 15, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Heroism: The Christian Ministry, April 19, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - God's Wishes for Man or the Proposals of the Gospel, September 18, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Faith Triumphant Over Failure, October 23, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Retrospection, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Christian Patriotism, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Gospel of the Kingdom, February 7, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Gospel of Jesus Christ, June 24, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - The Opportunity of Youth, July 22, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - The Serenity of Faith, July 29, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Master and Disciple, August 5, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Christmas 1894, October 23, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - The Kingdom of Christ, January 6, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Motives to a Christian Life, January 15, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Realities, March 10, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Our Patriotic Dead, May 30, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Our Future, July 28, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Moments of Power in Human Lives, July 28, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Persistency, August 4, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - The Purpose of the Gospel to Make Men and Women, August 18, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - The Unchangeable Christ, August 30, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - The Doctrine or Training of the Apostles, June 7, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Theories of Life, August 16, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - A Great Duty, August 23, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Characteristics of Christian Life, November 8, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - What the Church of Today Stands for, April 11, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Studies for the Bancroft, April 27, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Obedience is Better than Sacrifice, May 9, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Analysis for Persistency, June 3, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Teachings of Jesus Concerning Man and His Salvation; Origin of the Belief in the Incarnation, 1898 1907; 1898, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - The Thirty Years' War, February 15, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - A Vision of God the Interpretation of Life, July 3, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - The Gospel Proposals, September 24, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Working Together with God, October 1, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Christianity and the Intellectual Life, March 4, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - For the Bancroft, June 19, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Guilt and Danger of Moral Indifference, August 8, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Untitled sermon, April 1901 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - The Law of Self-Sacrifice, October 12, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Waiting for the Moving of the Water, November 30, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Christ as the Pledge of Immortality, December 7, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Untitled sermon, January 1903 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Untitled sermon, January 25, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Witnesses for Christ, February 1, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - What is it to be a Christian?, March 22, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - This Onething I Do, March 29, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Prayer Meeting on Hebrews, April 22, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Attraction to Christian Religion for Young Men, July 18, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Our Idea of a Priest, October 6, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Palm Sunday Entrance into Jerusalem, April 8, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - The Rich Young Ruler, November 6, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Majesty of Law and Blessedness of Obedience, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - A Lost Bible, March 10, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Does God Care?, August 11, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Vision through Christ, December 15, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - What Christ proposes to do for Men?, March 3, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - The Ideal Man Sermon, July 31, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - The Appeal of the Xtn Religion to the Present Generation, September 17, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Untitled sermon, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - The Significance of a Human Life, August 11, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Alone in the World, August 18, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - The Future Life, August 25, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Living in God, September 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - The Christian Life, September 8, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - The Stones, February 17 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Sermons Preached at 47th Street Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Studies on the Prophet, undated (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Theories of Evolution and Our Idea of God, undated (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Foundations of Every Acceptable Religious Service, undated (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - The New Birth, undated (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Evangelistic Services, undated (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Incomplete sermon on Europe and Asia, undated (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - The Problem of Suffering, undated (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Summary of the Synoptics, undated (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - What Men Want, undated (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - A Women's Evangelical, undated (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Sermon packets, undated (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Why should I be a Christian?, undated (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Ordination sermon, undated (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - The Salt of the World, undated (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - The Christian Religion: An Appeal for its Acceptance, undated (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Growth of the Christian Disciple, undated (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Untitled sermon, undated (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Worth of the Bible, undated (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - A Nation's Duty to Itself: A Patriotic Sermon, undated (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Church of the Living God, undated (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Loose pages from unknown sermons, undated (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Sermons first preached at Tabernacle Congregational Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Sermons preached at South Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Lectures, 1870 1918; 1870-1918; 21 Folders
  This series contains lectures that were given by Williams to Rochford Female Seminary and Beloit College.
  - Lectures at Rochford Female Seminary, 1870 1873; 1870-1873 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lectures at Rochford Female Seminary, 1873 1873; 1873, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lectures on Systematic Theology, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Beloit College lectures on Christian and Modern Ethics, May 1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Beloit College lectures on Greek Morality and Ethics, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Beloit College lectures on Socrates, Aristotle and Plato, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Beloit College lectures on Four Socratic Schools and Stoicism, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Beloit College lectures on Butler, Hume and Adam Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Beloit College lectures on the Intuitionalists, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Beloit College lectures on Utilitarianism, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Beloit College lectures General Summary, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Beloit College lectures on Christian and Medieval Ethics, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Beloit College lectures on Christian Ethics, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Beloit College lectures on Modern Ethics, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Beloit College lectures on Greek Philosophy, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Beloit College lectures on Weber's History of Philosophy, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Beloit College lectures on Philosophy, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Beloit College lectures on Christianity and Philosophy of the Middle Age, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Beloit College lectures on Philosophy and History, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Beloit College lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Second lecture on Hebrews, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)